<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gaines of seeking God In two sermons, preached in the parish church of VVestminster: by Christopher Styles.</title>
            <author>Styles, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857609</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857609</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13120)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 582:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gaines of seeking God In two sermons, preached in the parish church of VVestminster: by Christopher Styles.</title>
                  <author>Styles, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23370:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23370:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GAINES OF SEEKING GOD. In two Sermons, preached in the <hi>Pariſh Church of</hi> WEST<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINSTER: By <hi>Chriſtopher Styles.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ECCLVS 33.16.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold, how I haue not laboured only for my ſelfe, but for all them that ſeeke knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Stansby,</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:23370:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23370:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Sir HENRY HOBART, <hi>Knight and Baronet; Lord Chiefe</hi> Iuſtice of his Maieſties Court of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Pleas, and Chancellour to the</hi> PRINCE his Highneſſe: all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Graces, temporall Bleſſings, <hi>and eternall Happineſſe be multiplyed.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the aſſurance of ſome intereſt had in your Lordſhips ſauor (which I hope I haue not vtterly loſt) thogh it bee long ſince I was knowne vnto you, yet becauſe you were my firſt good Maſter, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom I ſerued, in your Church at <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merton</hi> in <hi>Norfolke,</hi> by the ſpace of foure yeeres; and
<pb facs="tcp:23370:3"/>more, till God prouided for me a good Liuing in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, which now I haue vnfortunately left: And now hauing a ſmall meanes to liue vpon by my great paines in the Pariſh of <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> being ſo neere to your Honour; and being requeſted to put this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in print, I am bold (as well to ſatisfie my good Friends requeſts, which were hearers of the ſame, as for the benefit of all well-diſpoſed Chriſtians) to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the ſame vnto your Lordſhips fauourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, for by your Honorable countenance I hope to reape much comfort for this my ſmall labour, I ayme at no other end in this Enterprize, but to ſhew my thankfulneſſe to your Honour, and to all my cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Neighbours, therefore if raſh and riotous Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, be neuer ſo enuious in their talke, againſt theſe my weake beginnings, yet if your Lordſhip be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to grace my good meaning, with your Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable countenance, I ſhall bee bound to pray daily for the continuance of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips health and proſperitie, and will euer remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips daily Orator and moſt dutifull Seruant, <hi>CHRISTOPHER STYLES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:23370:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, if with a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mind thou ſeekeſt onely to profit and comfort thy ſoule, and not by vaine and idle cauils <hi>(Nodum in ſcirpo quaerere)</hi> to find a fault not offered: I wiſh this Booke may be to thee as <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leach</hi> were to <hi>Iacob,</hi> fruitfull, and delightfull: and this I certifie to thee. I did not raſhly, but verie timorouſly, vndertake this burthen to content my friends, and could not be ſo much encouraged by many, as I was diſcouraged in my ſelfe: At last reſolued, becauſe the Method of my Teaching herein is only be way of exhortation, Paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically expounding euery word of my Text (which is not the moſt vnprofitable way whereby the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer may be edified) therefore I thought it might be acceptable, and this made me the bolder to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my Friends deſires, and publikely to make my ſelfe acquainted with your Chriſtian Carriages: Well-minded people will not deny my common Courteſie (that is) to iudge of my labors as if they were their owne: and this is all I aske.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C.S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:23370:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:23370:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE GAINES OF SEEKING GOD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 69.32.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Seeke after God, and your ſoule ſhall liue.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Booke of Pſalmes is a ſpirituall Librarie, whether the whole breadth of Scripture may be reduced for au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Scripture contained in this Book, we find it admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, as a Booke of abſolute Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie: and ſo approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued throughout the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>This Pſalme out of which I haue choſen my Text, is a liuely deſcription of the paſſions and patience of Chriſt, and his members (the Church.)</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:23370:5"/>
            <p>Theſe words which I haue choſen for my Text, are an holy inſtruction left for all Poſterities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are ſhewed the gaines of ſeeking God; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe we ſeeke for, our labour is but loſt, but in ſeeking after God, we ſhall enioy the fulneſſe of all true comfort to our ſoules, which only is in God; then ſeeke after God, and your ſoule ſhall liue.</p>
            <p>In theſe words of my Text, two things are to bee obſerued, firſt, a precept, (ſeeke after God) ſecondly, a promiſe, (and your ſoule ſhall liue.)</p>
            <p>In this precept alſo, three things are to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Firſt, how we ſhould ſeeke after God, and that muſt be <hi>(debito modo)</hi> in the right faſhion and order.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when wee ſhould ſeeke him, and that muſt bee <hi>(debito tempore)</hi> in a fit and right time.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, where to ſeeke God, and that muſt bee <hi>(debito loco)</hi> in the right place.</p>
            <p>Of theſe points only I purpoſe to entreate at this time, reſeruing the other part, which is the promiſe, vntill another Sabbath.</p>
            <p>For the firſt part of the precept, how wee ſhould ſeeke God, nature it ſelfe will teach vs, if wee haue loſt a Iewell which was moſt deare vnto vs, firſt, to ſeeke it in ſorrow for the loſſe: ſecondly, with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to regaine it: thirdly, with conſtant perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance till we haue found it.</p>
            <p>Oh, then let not the man endued with grace, plead ignorance in ſeeking God, but, firſt, <hi>lacrimabiliter,</hi> mournfully: ſecondly, <hi>diligenter,</hi> faithfully: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>perſeueranter,</hi> conſtantly in perſeuerance, neuer giue ouer vntill you find the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:23370:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The bleſſed Virgin <hi>Marie</hi> returning homewards from the Feaſt, and not finding him whom her ſoule loued (the child Ieſus) went back again to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> &amp; ſought him, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.48.</note> 
               <hi>Ego &amp; Pater tuus dolentes que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebamus te: Thy Father and I, haue ſought thee ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> And thus recouered ſhee the Iewell of her ioy.</p>
            <p>The ryotous Prodigall, hauing waſted all the Treaſure, by which he ſhould haue liued, and now remembring, how in his Fathers Houſe the hired Seruants had meat enough, and he was readie to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for hunger, hee ſought his Fathers loue againe, mournfully confeſſing, and ſaying, <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.18</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſinned, &amp;c. and ſo was receiued, with feaſting and ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marie Magdalene,</hi> out of whom Chriſt had caſt ſeuen Deuils, and was the only friend and comfort of her ſoule, when ſhee came to the Graue, and found him not there, ſhee bowed her ſelfe into the Graue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.13</note> 
               <hi>and wept, becauſe they had taken away her Lord, and ſhe knew not where they had layd him;</hi> and in this ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeeking, ſhe found him to her great comfort.</p>
            <p>Ieſus himſelfe while hee liued in the World was neuer ſeene to laugh, but often weeping.</p>
            <p>Wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi> in the depth of his Diuinitie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 2.2.</note> ſaid vnto mirth, what ayleſt thou? &amp; to laughter, thou art mad? Oh bleſſed Ieſu, how ſhould I thinke to find thee in pleaſure and ioy, whom thy Mother could ſcarce find with teares.</p>
            <p>Take heed therefore, you that feaſt it with <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> braue it with <hi>Haman,</hi> and carouſe it with <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar,</hi> and reuell with <hi>Herod,</hi> not at all regarding to ſeeke the Lord, leſt the Lord on a ſudden, deale
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23370:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>with you, as with them, and turne your feaſting into faſting, take the cup from your mouth, and fill you with ſpuing, turne you out of all your iollitie, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing perpetuall ſhame vpon you: this can God, and this will God doe, if you doe not humbly preuent his Iudgements, ſeeking to his mercie mournfully. Gods Wordes preuaile much with men, and more with God, but teares conſtraine compaſſion: our ſins are cauſe enough to weep for. <hi>Melt then your hearts in ſorrow for your ſinne,</hi> as holy <hi>Dauid</hi> did, whoſe heart in the middeſt of his bodie, was euen like mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Waxe: that God may quit your ſoules with peace, and ſeeke him <hi>(lachrimabiliter)</hi> mournfully.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in ſeeking after God, we muſt vſe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, without ſlothfull negligence, and ſeeke him <hi>(diligenter)</hi> diligently, as the woman in the Goſpell ſeeking her Groat that was loſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.8.</note> did light a Candle and ſweepe the houſe, and ſought diligently vntill ſhee found it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10</note> And as <hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſe Preacher hath taught thee, All that thine hand ſhall find to doe, doe it with all thy power.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſeeking the Lord, did ſeeke him with his whole heart, <hi>For you ſhall ſeeke mee with all your heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 29.14.</note> 
               <hi>and I will be found of you,</hi> ſaith the Lord. <hi>And if thou ſeeke the LORD with all thy heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.29.</note> 
               <hi>and with all thy ſoule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.26.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt finde him. For as Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger to the teeth, ſo is a ſlothfull body to them that ſend him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>ſleeper</hi> ſhall be clothed with ragges,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.21.</note> and he is denounced accurſed that doth the worke of the Lord negligently:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord loueth a cheerefull
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23370:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>giuer,</hi> (as <hi>Zacheus</hi>) <hi>and will be found of them that ſeeke him diligently,</hi> that is, <hi>faithfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuch is the madneſſe of this rude age wherein we liue, and the blindneſſe of worldly minded men, that they eſteeme no labour too much, in ſeeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter worldly gaine, which cannot profit them: and in ſeeking after the pleaſures of this life, which may much annoy them, but will not ſtep one foot towards Heauen, with an holy deſire to ſeeke after God. In whom is the fulneſſe of all true felicitie. The Apoſtle complained not without a cauſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>That all ſeeke their owne, and not the things of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> but if thou deſireſt to finde Heauen, ſeeke after God by Ieſus Chriſt, who is gone thither before to prepare a place for you, and ſeeke him <hi>(diligenter)</hi> with all your hearts, diligently.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wouldſt thou finde the Lord, thy only Comforter, ſeeke after him, <hi>(perſeueranter)</hi> conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with perſeuerance, and bee not weary of well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for in due ſeaſon yee ſhall reape, if yee faint not, therefore ſeeke the Lord and his face euermore.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>As the Spouſe neuer ceaſed to ſeeke him whom her ſoule lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, till ſhe found him and tooke hold of him, and left him not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Ship that hath made many a faire venture on the Sea, and after periſheth in the Hauen, brings loſſe and ſorrow to the Owner, that hoped for gaine. And a Souldier that fainteth before the battaile bee ended, muſt expect ſhame and death in ſtead of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie: So he that ſeeketh after God, and faileth in his intended courſe, before hee finde him, muſt needes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:23370:7"/>bring loſſe and ſorrow to his ſoule, and expect confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ſaluation. For the Crowue is giuen only to the Conquerour.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Be thou faithfull vnto the death, and I will giue thee the Crowne of life;</hi> the fire of Gods Altar muſt neuer goe out, ſo the zeale of a conſtant Profeſſor muſt not be extinguiſhed by worldly care. <hi>No man that putteth his hand to the Plough and looketh backe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.62.</note> 
               <hi>is apt to the Kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember <hi>Lots</hi> wife,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 19.</note> who for looking backe, was turned into a Pillar of Salt: And hauing once begun to ſeeke after God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1.</note> and to ſeeke thoſe things which are aboue, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20.</note> why as though yee liued in the World, are yee burthened with traditions: The Prophet teſtifieth that the life of a righteous man ſhall neuer fade;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.4.</note> and that the heart of a righteous man ſhall neuer faint;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.8.</note> if his faith were enioyned to ſeeke after God, through all the fierie tryalls of this World, and all the fierie flames and torments of Hell, it would not ſticke at the condition, being before with confidence perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.6.</note> That he that hath begunne this good worke in him, will performe it vntill the Day of Ieſus Chriſt. Thus muſt you ſeeke after God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17.</note> with a ſorrowfull heart, which he ſhall not deſpiſe; you muſt ſeeke him diligently that you may bee counted worthy to eſcape all thoſe things that ſhall come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>And that you may ſtand before the Sonne of man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36</note> and you muſt ſeeke him with perſeuerance, and neuer giue ouer for any temptation, leſt you fall away, for God is faithfull and will not ſuffer you to be tempted aboue that you bee able,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13</note> but will euen giue the iſſue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23370:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the temptation, thus: Thus, to ſeeke the Lord, alwayes longing after the God of our ſaluation, wee cannot choſe but finde the comforts of his graces in our ſoules, and bee aſſured to bee deliuered from the power of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13.</note> and to bee tranſlated into the Kingdome of his deare Sonne, whether hee bring vs all, that hath ſo dearely bought vs with his precious bloud, euen Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and only Sauiour, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard the manner how to ſeeke God: It followeth whereby we may learne the time when to ſeeke God, which is our ſecond obſeruation in my Text, as in the time of ſinne;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.14.</note> the luſts of our owne concupiſcence led vs aſtray from God, ſo now in the time of grace, through the preaching of the Goſpell, being led by the Spirit in the light of faith, wee make haſte to returne and ſeeke after God in whom alone we may find true reſt vnto our ſoules <hi>(de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bito tempore;)</hi> in a conuenient time. And as at al times, and in all places, it is meete to ſeeke vnto God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36</note> 
               <hi>Of whome, and through whome, and for whome wee liue and mooue, and haue our being.</hi> So wee are taught in holy Scriptures, of three times moſt conuenient to ſeeke after God; Firſt, <hi>(Dum dies eſt:</hi> Secondly, <hi>dum praeſens eſt:</hi> Thirdly, <hi>dum miſericors est.</hi>) Firſt, while it is day, <hi>Nicodemus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.2.</note> though hee was a Ruler of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and a Teacher in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hath this Record left in Scripture againſt him, that hee came to Ieſus by night.</p>
            <p>And the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> confeſſeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1.</note> why ſhe could not finde her Loue, that is, becauſe ſhee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23370:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſought him by night, and our Sauiour himſelfe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>The night commeth when no man can worke.</hi> In the night of Ignorance wee are more prone to ſeeke after Error, then the Truth; In the night of ſinne, we ſeeke for the things that pleaſe men, and not the things that pleaſe God, and in the night of death, we ſhall not bee able to ſeeke at all: <hi>For who ſhall giue thee thankes in the pit?</hi> therefore holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the God of his ſaluation deferres no time, <hi>But flyeth to the Lord before the morning watch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.1. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33 3.</note> 
               <hi>and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth early to ſeeke after God:</hi> King <hi>Ioſia,</hi> when hee was but yet a childe, <hi>began to ſeeke after the God of his Father Dauid. Verily, the children of this World are wiſe in their generation, obſeruing dayes, and moneths, and yeeres, and times, and ſhall the ſonnes of men har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den their hearts;</hi> God ſpeaketh by his holy Prophet, <hi>To day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.8.</note> 
               <hi>if you will heare my voyce, &amp;c.</hi> and ſhall wee harden our hearts to day, and let ſinne grow till to morrow.</p>
            <p>Shall wee giue the crop to Satan, and ſet God to gleaning, who knoweth if he ſhall liue, repent, or eſcape. Suddenly may his wrath bee kindled, and in the time of vengeance he will deſtroy. Our Life is the Way, Heauen is the Countrey: here make thy peace with God, that he may receiue thee there, vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorie for euermore. Thus ſeeke to God while it is day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſeeke after God <hi>(debito tempore)</hi> in time of oportunitie, is, while be is preſent, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.6.</note> 
               <hi>Seek the Lord while he may be found, and call vpon him while he is nigh.</hi> It is anexcellent example to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23370:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>vs, in obſeruing the fitteſt time to ſeeke God, if wee conſider the complaint of the Spouſe in the <hi>Cantic.</hi> ſaying, <hi>It is the voyce of my Beloued that knocketh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſaying, open to me, my Siſter, my Loue, my Doue, my Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, for my head is full of dew, and my lockes with the drops of the night</hi> (all bleſſings and happineſſe are now to bee receiued at the hands of God) <hi>whileſt hee is preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But whileſt ſhe roſe to put on her Coate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>her Beloued was gone, I ſought him (ſaid ſhee) but I could not finde him, I called him but hee anſwered not:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.10</note> 
               <hi>So the fooliſh Virgins had the doore ſhut while they fetch Oyle:</hi> This World is the ſeed place, Heauen is the reaping place, here they that ſowe in teares, ſhall reape their ioy in Heauen; as this day leaues vs, ſo ſhall that day finde vs; now God is preſent vnto all, then only vnto his: <hi>I goe my way and ye ſhall ſeeke me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>and yee ſhall die in your ſinnes, for whither I goe, yee cannot come.</hi> Now, therefore ſeeke to follow after God, moſt ſweet, moſt mightie, &amp; moſt wiſe: therfore he will receiue vs gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>(Eum qui venit ad me, non reijcio foras)</hi> Hee that commeth to me, I caſt not out of doores: moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, all power belongeth vnto God, he will defend vs ſtoutly, <hi>If the Lord be on my ſide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.6.</note> 
               <hi>I will not feare what man can doe vnto me,</hi> moſt wiſe, ſo he will lead vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to happineſſe: becauſe you haue followed me in the Regeneration, <hi>You ſhall ſit vpon twelue Thrones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28</note> 
               <hi>and iudge the twelue Tribes of Iſrael,</hi> as a ſtone caſt vp, reſts not but in the center: ſo let all them that are caſt forth into the world, not reſt, but in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Domine fecisti nos ad te, &amp;c.)</hi> O Lord, thou haſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:23370:9"/>made vs for thy ſelfe, and we can find no reſt vnto our ſoules, but in thy ſelfe: Art thou ſicke of ſinne; <hi>The whole need not the Phiſician, but the ſicke; I came not to call the Righteous, but Sinners, to repentance.</hi> Art thou oppreſt with pouertie, caſt all your care on him, for he careth for you? The Earth is the Lords (which if he giues thee not, he hath reſerued Heauen for thee) a happie exchang! Art thou grieued with diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; the rebukes of the fooliſh, the ſcorne of the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and the diſdaine of the proud, hee brings thee glorie for thy ſhame? Therefore open the gates, O ye righteous, and the King of glorie ſhall come in, while he is preſent: what wouldſt thou haue that thou maiſt not? what wouldſt thou be that thou canſt not? if now thou ſeekeſt after God, who is able to giue all things, and will deny thee nothing whileſt he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>(Nunc vacatur Deus negotijs noſtris.)</hi> Now God hath taken time to heare our complaints, to plead with man, and to furniſh the lower World, and all things contained therein, with the rich bleſsings of his loue; whilſt therfore he is preſent to heare thee, whilſt he is preſent to helpe thee, abſent not thy ſelfe by ſin; but ſeeke after God whileſt he is preſent with thee.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if you will ſeeke after God <hi>(debito tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore)</hi> faile not to do it <hi>(dum miſericors eſt)</hi> while he is mercifull. He that hath a ſuite to his King, will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a time when he may find him beſt pleaſed; now is the time of mercie, now euery one that ſeekes God faithfully, ſhall find him ioyfully, but when he hath begun to iudge in Righteouſneſſe, that ſhall bee the time of Iudgement, not of Mercie: When the good
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23370:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>man of that houſe is riſen vp, and hath ſhut too the doore, and yee beginne to ſtand without, and to knocke at the doore, ſaying, <hi>Lord, open vnto vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.25</note> 
               <hi>hee ſhall tell you, I know you not, whence yee are, Depart yee workers of iniquitie, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth:</hi> yet therefore let him that hath continued in ſinne, ten, twentie, thirtie yeeres and more; turne vnto God that he may haue mercie vpon him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 3.18.</note> for <hi>yet will the Lord waite that hee may haue mercie vpon you, and be exalted for his compaſsion;</hi> and ſurely great is the mercie of God in exſpecting our conuerſion, for he would not beare with the <hi>Angels</hi> but caſt them downe from Heauen ſuddenly like Lightning, for but once ſinning againſt him; he alſo baniſht the firſt man out of Paradiſe for breaking one Commandement: but hee hath borne with vs a long time, and we haue broken all his Lawes, ſtill exſpecting our conuerſion till our laſt age. <hi>(Nolo mortem peccatoris)</hi> I will not the death of a Sinner, therefore cauſe one another to returne and liue, but he that will not bee conuerted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11</note> and becauſe ſentence is not ſpeedily executed againſt euery euill worke, doth fully ſet his heart in them to doe euill, ſhall ſurely ſuffer the greater Iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Nam quos hic diu longanimiter portat, Illos Deus grauius damnat)</hi> The longer God forbeareth a ſinner, the more grieuous ſhall his puniſhment be at laſt, as in the examples of <hi>Pharaoh, Sodome,</hi> the olde World, and the <hi>Iewes.</hi> Now cryes <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Make ſtraight the way of the Lord, this is the time of mercie.</hi> Now cryes Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>I am the doore, by mee, if any man enter in, he ſhall be ſaued.</hi> Now doth the Spirit
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23370:10"/>and the Bride ſay, <hi>Come, &amp; let him that is a thirſt come; and let whoſoeuer will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 22.17.</note> 
               <hi>take of the water of Life freely; For, behold, I come ſhortly, and my reward is with mee, to giue euery man according as his worke ſhall be:</hi> (who will not be drawne by loue, ſhall bee driuen by feare) now God puniſheth man of his mercie, that ſo hee might conuert him to himſelfe: the euils which wee ſuffer in this life compeld vs to go vnto God: happy is that miſerie that vrgeth vs to be better. Thoſe whom Chriſt hereafter (if they continue in ſinne) will puniſh with confuſion (if they repent) hee receiueth them here with mercie, to the end, hereafter, to crowne them for euer with glorie, as he did <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene,</hi> repenting: The prodigall confeſſing, the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple denying, and the Thiefe of the Croſſe conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Lord, teach vs ſo to number our dayes, that wee may apply our hearts vnto wiſdome, and turne to thee in time, while the day of our life ſhall laſt, and while thou art preſent, in thy fauour towards vs. And whiles thou art a mercifull God vnto vs, and thus ſeeking, ſo let vs find thee for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you haue bin inſtructed in the manner how to ſeeke God, and the time when, It followeth neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, you ſhould learne the place where to ſeeke God, which is the third circumſtance of our firſt obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeeke him in <hi>(debito loco)</hi> in the right place, God is not in the ſtrong wind of pleaſure and delight,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Rin.</hi> 19.11.</note> that makes ſo many ſwell in vanitie: God is not in the Earth-quake of couetouſneſſe, which puts the ſoule in danger of a diſmall downfall: God is not in the fire of ſloth, that conſumes the ſoules eſtate in grace, by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23370:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>luſtfull cogitations, but in the ſoft ſtil voyce of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, Contemplation, and Prayer; therefore to ſeeke him in the right place, <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39.</note> 
               <hi>and they ſhall tell you of me.</hi> Inquire there and thou ſhalt finde him <hi>(In praecepio humilitatis pauperibus)</hi> In the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Humilitie, preſenting himſelfe to the poore <hi>(In deſerto contemplationis vigilantibus)</hi> In the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Contemplation, declaring glad tydings to the watchfull <hi>(In Templo exorationis diſputantibus)</hi> In his holy Houſe the Temple of Prayer, ſpeaking peace to his people, that call vpon his Name, there and no where elſe canſt thou find him, who deſires to ſeeke elſe-where, muſt goe out of the World.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if you will ſeeke him in the right place,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.12</note> you ſhal find him <hi>(In praecepio humilitatis pauperibus)</hi> You ſhall finde the Babe ſwadled, and layd in a Manger. This was to giue vs an example of perfect Humility, and Patience, and how to embrace Pouerty; all which he hath euen choſen as his one part, that wee might neuer deſpayre being his partners;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.5.</note> 
               <hi>For who is like the Lord our God, who hath his dwelling ſo high, yet hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth himſelfe to behold the things that are in Heauen and Earth.</hi> And thus ſaith the holy One,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.5.</note> 
               <hi>I dwelt in the high and holy place with him alſo that is of an humble and contrite ſpirit, to receiue the ſpirit of the humble, and to giue life to the contrite heart:</hi> bee not diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with thy pouertie, for nothing can bee found ſo profitable for thee, Heauen is the purchaſe of the poore, and it is the ſumme of Religion, to imitate his example whom thou doeſt worſhip, and, <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 9.58.</note> 
               <hi>the Sonne of man hath not where to lay his head.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:23370:11"/>
            <p>All the Saints of God wandred vp and downe, <hi>In Sheepes skinnes and Goat skinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37.</note> 
               <hi>deſtitute, afflicted, and tormented,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>im.</hi> 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>whom the World was not worthy of: Therefore hauing food and rayment, let vs therewith be content to follow after Righteouſneſſe and Godlineſſe, and to finiſh our courſe in patience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.24</note> 
               <hi>Conſider the Rauens, they neither ſow, nor reape, neither haue Store-houſe nor Barn, yet our heauenly Father feedeth them; How much are yee better then the Fowles. Conſider the Lillies, they neither labour nor ſpinne, yet</hi> Salomon <hi>in all his Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was not clothed like one of theſe, If God ſo clothe the Graſſe of the Field, how much more will hee clothe them that truly obey him, Therefore aske not what yee ſhall eat or drinke, or wherewith you ſhall be clothed, for all ſuch things the people of the World ſeeke for, but ſeeke you after God, and the Kingdome of God, and the Righteouſneſſe thereof, and all theſe things ſhall bee caſt vpon you. (ſo farre as they ſhall be neceſſarie and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for you.)</hi> Thy Sauiour Chriſt, deſpiſe the World, our fore-fathers in Chriſt, and all the holy Saints of God, did vſe the World as if they vſed it not, and who would not gladly loſe the World to winne Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. The ioyes of this World are but the Deuils Poyſons: heere are no true ioyes, but there are the true ioyes placed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.5.</note> where the true life is gone before; <hi>And why ſeeke you the liuing amongſt the dead, He is riſen, hee is not here.</hi> The comfort of light is beſt knowne in darkneſſe, of health in ſickneſſe, of honour in baſeneſſe, all theſe mayſt thou finde in God, not in the World: thus hee hath made our life tedious and full of troubles, leſt being delighted in the way, wee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23370:11"/>ſhould forget the Country whereto we are trauelling, for we haue here no continuing Citie, but ſeeke on to come euen a houſe not made with hands, but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the Heauens, oh, ſeeke him thus, <hi>(debito loco)</hi> in the right place,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.6.</note> 
               <hi>That he may lift thy poore ſoule out of the myre of afflictions, and ſet thee with the Princes and Saints in Heauen for euermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeke him <hi>(debito loco)</hi> in the right place, ſeeke him in <hi>(in deſerto contemplationis)</hi> in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of Contemplation, all you that wayte in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence while the Lord ſhall come in power to deliuer you out of all your feare; behold, I will allure her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſe</hi> 2.14.</note> and bring her into the Wilderneſſe, and ſpeake friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to her <hi>(in ſolitudine gratia conſeruatur)</hi> in deſart places and ſolitarie, a man is made more apt for Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: therefore <hi>Iſaack</hi> went forth to pray in the field toward the Euening,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.63</note> and Ieſus ſent away his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and went into the Deſart alone to pray.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 4.1.</note> The Angels found Ieſus in the Wilderneſſe tempted; much likelier it is we ſhall be tempted in the Cities of Societie, ſeeing all companies <hi>(aut pares querunt aut faciunt)</hi> doe ſeeke their like, or doe make them ſo, that keepe companie with them. And it is certaine <hi>(qui iunguntur in peccato, ne ſeperantur in poena)</hi> they that ioyne together in the ſame ſinne, ſhall not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the ſame puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Thy ſoule being eaſilier loſt in companie then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ſhould therefore liue alone, that ſhe may pleaſe him alone, whom ſhe hath choſen alone.</p>
            <p>Thy beloued (oh ſoule) is ſhamefaſt, and is vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſhew thee familiaritie in the common pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23370:12"/>Leaue therefore publike companie, yea, leaue thy priuate family, and receiue the bleſſing of his loue alone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.11.</note> (heare what hee ſaith) <hi>Come, my well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, let vs goe forth into the field, let vs get vp early to ſee if the Vine flouriſh, if ſhee hath budded the ſmall Grape, or whether the Pomegranets flouriſh, there will I giue thee my Loue.</hi> Againe <hi>(in ſolitudine cum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis conuerſatur)</hi> In ſolitarie places Angels haue oft beene ſeene to conuerſe with men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> was comforted by the Angels in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.2.</note> as he fled from his Brother <hi>Eſau. Moſes</hi> was inſtructed by the Angell of God in the flaming Buſh in the Wilderneſſe, what hee ſhould doe to deliuer Gods people out of bondage.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.11.</note> The Angels came and comforted <hi>Ieſus</hi> in the Wilderneſſe after hee was tempted of the Deuill. The farther from the World, the neerer to God: as an Apple-tree planted where the branches ſpread ouer a common way; thoſe bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſo ſpreading are alwayes ſubiect to ſpoyle, and are made a prey to euery Paſſenger, but thoſe that grow in the compaſſe of the Owners ground, beare fruit vnto the Planters profit; ſo the man that ſpreads his heart to entertayne the World cannot keepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie to the end, whereby it often falls out that God loſeth his due, which is their heart, and they their deſire, which is Heauen; as in the example of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.5.</note> Againe <hi>(In ſolitudine ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum malignorum euitatur)</hi> In deſart and ſolitarie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wee eſcape the poyſon of ſlanderous tongues, therfore <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> being to prepare the way of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.1.</note> had his continuall abode in the Wilderneſſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23370:12"/>where he taught all that came vnto him: When God gaue <hi>Iſrael</hi> a Law, it was in the Wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 19.20.</note> where he ſpake vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.1.</note> When <hi>Ieſus</hi> made that heauenly Sermon to the multitude, he went into a deſart place, and there taught them from the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; by which examples wee are learned that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer will bee good Teachers, and good Hearers, muſt ſeparate themſelues ſometimes, and for the moſt part, from common and publike Societies: for in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart and ſolitarie places, the minde is inlightened, ſo it fared with that great King <hi>Nabuchadnezzar,</hi> who ſecing nothing but confuſion, while hee liued in his ſtately Palace at great <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.34.</note> could yet behold Gods glorie in the Heauens, being baniſhed: alſo in deſart and ſolitarie places, the heart is inflamed with good deſires,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudith</hi> 8.5.</note> therefore <hi>Iudith</hi> built her Oratorie in the top of her houſe, that the priuateneſſe of the place might increaſe the zeale of her affection: alſo in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart and ſolitary places, the ſoule is often rauiſhed with the contemplation of Heauens ſweetneſſe, as <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt being baniſhed into the Ile <hi>Path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. tot.</note> writ a whole Booke of ſweet Reuelations there. I ſpeake not this to animate our Separatiſts, whoſe daily practice is to draw the Communion of Chriſts Church into priuate Conuenticles, but of the muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous multitude of this Age, that ioyne hand in hand, and haue all one Purſe, and are all of one minde, to doe euill, and to worke all vncleanneſſe, euen with greedineſſe: theſe, yea theſe are they, whom I would haue, and whome I doe beſeech, to conſider of their wayes, and workes, by themſelues alone, and of Gods
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23370:13"/>preſence, inſtantly able to reward euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as his workes ſhall be, leſt the Lord ſhould ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly plucke them away; when they ſhall finde none to reſcue them, thus by priuate conference, (Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Abſolution) betweene their ſoules and God, let them ſeeke out of deſart places, euen ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God by themſelues alone, that ſo they may taſte the ſweetneſſe of Gods grace and mercie, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of their ſoules for euermore.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wouldſt thou know where to ſeeke God <hi>(debito loco)</hi> come to the Temple, where the lips of the wiſe preſerue knowledge, they ſhal counſaile thee <hi>(in templo exorationis)</hi> in the Temple of Prayer, God ſtandeth alwayes readie to heare all thoſe that call vpon his Name, and to anſwere all their ſoules that deſire inſtruction. There you cannot faile to heare of him: for in his Temple doth euery man ſpeake of his honour. When <hi>Salomon</hi> prayed in the Temple, and offered vnto the Lord a Sacrifice,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 9.3</note> then God promiſed his bleſſing to that houſe for euer: When King <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechia</hi> ſpred the blaſphemous Letter of rayling <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhakeh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 19.14.</note> before the Lord in the Temple, God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to deliuer the King, and put his foes to confuſion. We reade of <hi>Ieſus</hi> in the Temple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.45</note> how he whipt out the Marchants: poſed the Doctors; and daily taught the people.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He whipt out the Marchants, ſaying, <hi>My Houſe ſhall be called the Houſe of Prayer, but you haue made it a Den of Theeues,</hi> (marke I pray you) he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth none to buy and ſell, but taught the mall, that came to heare and pray: ſuch ſtill are welcome to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23370:13"/>their Sauiour: but in this monſtrous Age, moſt doe come to make marchandize, both in and of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Some make marchandize in the Temple, and teach not the way of God truely, but for feare or flatterie, ſpeake not at all, or ſpeake pleaſing things, and ſpare to tell the houſe of <hi>Iudah</hi> their tranſgreſſions, and the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> their ſinnes, that they might forſake their wicked wayes and turne againe vnto the Lord and liue. And ſome make marchandize of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and are not at reſt til the Houſe of God lye waſte,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.4.</note> or if not quite waſte, yet more then halfe ſpoyled: dealing with the Lmbaſſadours of the Lord, as the Princes of the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> dealt with the Meſſengers of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ſhared of the halfe of their beard,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 10.4.</note> and cut off their Garments in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, ſo too many at this day haue ſpoyld the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Temple, ſtrangely metamorphoſing Parſonages into Vicarages, and Vicarages into Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, and Donatiues into Penſions, leauing ſcarce the price of a Liuerie for the Prieſt, that wayteth on the Altar, and ſhould liue of the Altar.</p>
            <p>But the Lord will one day come againſt them as he came againſt <hi>Antiochus</hi> that ſought to deſtroy the Temple of God, he did it not,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.5.</note> but while he thought to doe it (marke that) the Lord plagued him with a Diſeaſe in his bowels, inuiſible, and incurable, ſo that he died: ſo you that now liue of the ſpoyles of the Temple, God will one day whip you out with a rod of Iron.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Ieſus</hi> was found in the Temple poſing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23370:14"/>the Doctors: a good Leſſon for vs all to learne: Firſt, for vs Miniſters, for hee that deſireth the office of a Biſhop muſt be apt to teach, being ſufficiently inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to conuince Hereſie, to exhort vnto Godlineſſe, and to rebuke them that ſinne before all, that others alſo may feare, or elſe he is vnworthy to bee a Maſter vnto the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, if hee bee ignorant of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Secondly, here is a good Leſſon for you to learne, that come to the Temple and Houſe of God, to bee made partakers of his holy Word, come not hither, to heare the Preacher, as the <hi>Iewes</hi> came to heare Chriſt, that they might intangle him in his talke, nor as <hi>Herod</hi> who heard <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> gladly, yet cut off his head, nor in preſumption with the <hi>Iewes</hi> to teach your Teachers: if you doe? then as Chriſt ſaith, take heed how you heare. And know that all wee that haue our errand from Heauen, and are called of God as <hi>Aaron</hi> was, haue knowledge ioyned with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſufficient, without feare of them that haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to kill the bodie, but are not able to kill the ſoule, boldly to preach the Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus euen before Kings, and to make you tremble at our Doctrine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25.</note> as <hi>Foelix</hi> did to heare <hi>Paul</hi> preach of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And can ſo eaſily confute ſuch buſie Ignorants, that they ſhall willingly confeſſe vnto their ſhame; we teach as men hauing authoritie, &amp; not as the Scribes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Ieſus ſate daily in the Temple to teach the people: he that will take the fleece, muſt feed the flocke.</p>
            <p>For whoſoeuer ſhall periſh in thy Fold (for want
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23370:14"/>of inſtruction) his ſoule will I require at thy hands, ſaith the Lord; and my ſheepe heare my voyce (marke that) if it be our dutie to teach, its your duty to heare. Therefore, I admoniſh you all, examine your ſelues how you haue profited in the Schoole of Chriſt, long hath the holy Goſpell beene taught vnto vs, if we be not bettered by theſe holy Councels, its a ſure token, that we haue not yet ſought after God <hi>(debito modo)</hi> as we ought, with our whole heart, mournfully by Repentance; diligently ſeeking nothing but God, conſtantly not fainting till wee find his Spirit anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſpirits in loue. Its alſo an infallible token of our irregular life, careleſſe of our ſmall time of abode, in that we will not ſeeke him <hi>(debito tempore)</hi> while it is day watchfully: while he is preſent cheerefully, while he is mercifull acceptably. Its alſo a manifeſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of our contempt againſt God refuſing to come where God is, for the Lord is in his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.4.</note> therefore wee muſt ſeeke him <hi>(debito loco)</hi> In his Temple, to powre out our hearts in Prayer before him: In his Temple to learne inſtruction, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline our hearts to vnderſtanding. In his Temple reuerently to obey our ſpirituall Teachers, and not to reſiſt the authoritie of their Doctrine nor to make difference of the holy Word of God, and of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, by hauing in reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, any man, but only for the words ſake.</p>
            <p>Thus to ſeeke after God <hi>(debito modo, debito tempore, debito loco)</hi> we ſhall be ſure to find him with ioy vnto our ſoules: which bleſſing God grant vnto vs all, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:23370:15"/>
            <head>THE GAINES OF SEEKING GOD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 69.32.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Seeke after God, and your ſoule ſhall liue.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text I partly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before, leauing the reſt till now: then I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided it into two parts, firſt, a Precept, in theſe words, <hi>Seeke after God:</hi> ſecondly, a Promiſe, in theſe words, <hi>and your ſoule ſhall liue.</hi> The firſt part, which is the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, I handled then at large, of the ſecond part which is the Promiſe, I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe now to treate, and doe humbly beſeech Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God his aſſiſtance, and your gentle patience.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:23370:15"/>
            <p>Here indeed is the true <hi>gaines of ſeeking after God,</hi> for ſo ſaith my Text, <hi>(your ſoule ſhall liue)</hi> In the handling whereof, theſe are the chiefe points where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to inſiſt: firſt, the dignitie conceiued in the Word <hi>(ſoule:)</hi> ſecondly, the qualitie in the Word <hi>(your:)</hi> thirdly, the vtilitie and comfort of the ſoule, in theſe words <hi>(ſhall liue.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the dignitie of the ſoule fitly mentioned in the verie Word it ſelfe <hi>(ſoule)</hi> ſhall more plainly bee conceiued in the conſideration of theſe three circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: firſt, the condition of the ſoule, while wee conſider the matter and eſſence whereof the ſoule conſiſteth. For, behold, In the ſoules Creation God only made it according to his owne Image, a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and incorporeall ſubſtance: And <hi>Augustine</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning about the ſoule, ſaith thus <hi>(Anima est incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porea ſubſtantia regens corpus, ſicut enim in Deo vna est eſſentia, &amp; tres distinctae perſonae: ſic in anima vna est eſſentia &amp; tres diſtinctae potentiae, Memoria, Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia, Voluntas)</hi> which is thus in Engliſh: <hi>The ſoule is a ſpirituall ſubſtance, gouerning the bodie, for as in God there is but one eſſence, and three diſtinct perſons: ſo in the ſoule there is but one eſſence and three distinct powers, that is, the Memorie, the Vnderſtanding, and the Will;</hi> (but howſoeuer) the immortalitie of the ſoule may be proued in this, in that it neuer ceaſeth to liue, euen in miſerie.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the dignitie and excellent nature of the ſoule, for according to the Image of God, the ſoule is made reaſonable, and may bee imployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout euery thing, but cannot bee ſatisfied with any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:23370:16"/>thing, for it being made capeable of God, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is leſſe then God, is vnable to fill it.</p>
            <p>O noble Creature, thou ſoule, which art only or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned for the fruition and viſion of God, O my ſoule that art formed in the Image of God, betrothed by faith, and indued with the Spirit, loue him, O loue him, of whom thou art ſo much beloued, O knit thy heart vnto him, that hath knit himſelfe to thy ſoule, and ſeeke after him that ſeeketh for thee, O ſeeke after God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But alas, for the ſtiffe-necked, hard-hearted Sinner, what ſhall become of thee, why doe you ſo neglect the ſaluation of your ſoules which are immortall.</p>
            <p>If thou diddeſt truely know the dignitie of thy ſelfe, O ſoule, whoſoeuer thou beeſt, thy ſins would be abominable vnto thee: a noble ſpirited man ſcorns rude and baſe companions, and all men naturally doe ſhunne the plague, and their deareſt friends poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt therewith: There is nothing ſo baſe as ſinne, the verie plague and infection of the ſoule: Oh then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and loath thy deareſt affections ſo long as they are in loue with ſinne, and let the conſideration of thy ſoules dignitie keepe thee in innocencie for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>The ſecond circumſtance to be conſidered, whereby we may know the dignitie of the ſoule (is by compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) wherein it ſhall appeare, how infinitely the ſoule exceeds the bodie with all the members thereof, and all things whatſoeuer haue beene created beſides: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſoule is better then euery body, for that that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life, is better then that which receiueth it, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23370:16"/>the ſoule giueth life to the bodie: yea, ſo much as the Firmament of Heauen is more beautifull then the Earth: ſo farre doth the ſoule exceede in glorie the beautifulleſt bodie that euer was framed. O how ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable is the diuers coloured beautie of all the Eſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of all the celeſtiall Firmament, how plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and profitable vnto vs, and how neceſſarie the ſeruice of them is for vs, and yet all theſe were made but for the ſoule: thou, O God, that haſt made all things, haſt placed &amp; ſubiected all theſe things vnder mans feet: that only Man remaining Lord ouer all thy Workes, ſhould himſelfe remayne only thine, and which is more, all outward things are created &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned for the bodie, but the bodie it ſelfe is ſubiect to the ſoule, and the ſoule it ſelfe is ſubiect vnto thee, that it might only ſerue thee, only loue thee, and only poſſeſſe thee alone. The price of the whole Word is not to be valued to the worth of the ſoule; for what ſhall it profit a man to winne the whole World and loſe his owne ſoule. Wee reade that the holy Saints haue crucified their owne bodies, and chaſtized themſelues with hard penance, and all that they might ſaue their ſoules:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>For they that are Chriſts haue crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts of it:</hi> O you holy Saints, and deareſt friends of God, tell vs, O tell vs, why with ſo many Watchings, ſo many Prayers, and ſo much Diſcipline, you haue ſo cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mortified your fleſh.</p>
            <p>O moſt glorious Martyrs, why haue you expoſed your ſelues to ſuch cruell torments, that you haue not refuſed to die, yea, euen a violent death, with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:23370:17"/>cheerfulneſſe embracing ſuch a ſentence? O bleſſed Ieſus, why diddeſt thou ſuffer three and thirtie yeeres together, hunger, thirſt, labour, ſweat, deepe wounds, and finally death it ſelfe, they anſwere all aloude, it was for the ſoule? therefore it is manifeſt the ſoule is more precious then all the other things of the world: Seeing then all things are but vile in compariſon of the ſoule, why doe wee ſo vainly care for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of euery thing but the ſoule: our bodies, our riches, our cattell, our garments are curiouſly deckt and prouided for, but alas, few men haue any reſpect at all vnto their ſoules, O vnhappie wretched men, why are you ſo carefull about many things, nay, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, ſauing this one thing, for which all your care ſhould be beſtowed?</p>
            <p>Remember Chriſts counſell to <hi>Maries</hi> complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Siſter (<hi>Martha, Martha,</hi> thou careſt and art troubled for many things, but one thing only is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, O then, beloued in the Lord, let vs louingly care for this one thing (our ſoule) in the faithfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation whereof conſiſteth all things elſe that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to mans eternall happineſſe, which God giue vs grace truly to performe for euer more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third circumſtance to be conſidered, whereby to know the dignitie of the ſoule, is by the habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being capeable of ſuch a glorious Tenant as the Holy Ghoſt for God hath created the ſoule to no other end but for himſelfe, which is to be his habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that the ſoule is called the Temple of God, As the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Know yee not that yee are the Temple of the Holy Ghost, and that the Spirit of God
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23370:17"/>dwelleth in you (if you bee the holy ſeate of God)</hi> thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Sauiour comming to keepe perpetuall Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, hath ordayned all things neceſſarie for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his entertaynment. So long as God dwels in the ſoule of a iuſt man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1.</note> 
               <hi>Hee hath commanded an Host of Angels to guard him; Hee ſhall giue his Angels charge ouer thee, to keepe thee in all thy wayes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7.</note> 
               <hi>And the Angell of the Lord tarryeth round about them that feare him, to deliuer them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold, the dignitie of the ſoule, how God hath appointed the Angels, that are ſo noble Creatures, to bee their keepers; Man made lower then the Angels, yet, lo, attended by them: Surely, its great dignitie to the ſoule, that euery man at his birth hath an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell choſen to bee his keeper; And this Angell is ſo employed about our buſineſſe, as a Meſſenger alwaies running betwixt the Beloued and her Loue, offering our Deſires and Prayers, as an acceptable Sacrifice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and bringing downe the Royall Preſent of Gods holy Gifts into the ſoule, ſtill ſtirring vp the ſoule to all good workes, and labouring to appeaſe Gods wrath, that it ſhould neuer bee kindled againſt vs: this Royal prerogatiue of the ſoule, to entertayne God as a Gheſt, truely deſcribes the dignitie of the ſame, which all this while is attended with an Armie of heauenly Souldiers.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 6.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, whileſt God inhabiteth the righteous ſoule, he makes it a continuall feaſt, in the large open Chamber of a quiet conſcience, and giues them the Bread of Life to feed vpon, euen by breaking his owne precious Bodie vnto them, the effect of bread
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:23370:18"/>is to preſerue life, and to ſtrenghten mans heart: So Chriſt that is the true Bread come downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, giueth them ſpirituall Bread (his Bodie) thereby to preſerue the life of the ſoule; <hi>Labour not then for the meate that periſheth, but for the meate that endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to euerlaſting life, which the Sonne of man ſhall giue vnto you, for him hath the Father ſealed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, yet whileſt God in habiteth the righteous ſoule, hee bringeth her a greater bleſſing then <hi>Caleb</hi> could beſtow vpon his Danghter, although hee gaue her the Springs aboue &amp; the Springs beneath, a rich Dowrie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 15.19.</note> For, whereas <hi>Man by nature and ſinne is made barren of all Grace,</hi> yet being bathed and waſhed in the euer-ſtreaming Fountaine of Chriſts Bloud by Repentance, and renewed by the Grace that is brought vnto her through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. She is made fruitfull in euery good worke, and to walke acceptably before God.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſhewing the <hi>Corinthians, That the vnrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of GOD,</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but yee are ſanctified:</hi> behold the dignitie of the ſoule, in the eſtimation of her price; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>yee are bought with a price:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20</note> 
               <hi>Great is the price of the ſoule, whome nothing could redeeme but the bloud of Ieſus Christ:</hi> God make vs carefull of this dignitie for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond place we are to conſider the qualitie of the ſoule, which may bee vnderſtood in the three powers of the ſoule, which I told you of before, and is mentioned in this word <hi>(your.)</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:23370:18"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>(Sapientiam docet)</hi> It teacheth vs Wiſedome: Secondly, <hi>(Munditiam ſeruat)</hi> It preſerueth vs in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie: Thirdly, <hi>(Conſtantiam nutrit)</hi> it nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our Conſtancie, who were elſe vtterly vnable to fight that great and tedious battaile betweene vs &amp; our ſpirituall enemies. It teacheth vs wiſedome three wayes, <hi>(intelligende praeterita)</hi> by vnderſtanding the things long ſince paſt. <hi>(Iudicanda praeſentia)</hi> in being able to diſcerne and iudge of thoſe things that bee now preſent; <hi>(Expectando futura)</hi> in expecting good things to bee receiued hereafter at the hands of God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>(Intelligendo praeterita, bona Animae Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae)</hi> Wiſedome is the treaſure of the ſoule, a good man knoweth all things which God hath made to be knowne, aſwell thoſe things of the World which are paſt, as the things that are to come, euen the inuiſible things of God, that is, his eternall Power and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, are ſeene by the Creation of the World, being conſidered in the Creatures his Workes: This made <hi>Dauid</hi> ſing, <hi>The Heauens declare the glorie of God, and the Fi mament ſheweth his handy-worke:</hi> the ſoule is only capeable of Reaſon, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the worthineſſe of her ſelfe, the vileneſſe of the bodie, and the ſhortneſſe of this life; therefore ſhe chuſeth rather to prouide for the Life to come which is immortall, then to regard at all this life which is ſo tranſitorie, this makes vs to worſhip God, before whom wee muſt ſtand to render our account at the Day of Iudgement: this made holy <hi>Dauid faithfully to apply his heart vnto Wiſedome, after hee knew how few dayes he had to liue:</hi> this knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:23370:19"/>is the true difference betweene Man and Beaſt, and therefore wee reade of <hi>Pauls</hi> complaint, that he had fought with Beaſts at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> after the manner of men, that is, beaſtly men, carnally mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing earthly things, but not ſauouring the things of God: and ſurely, he that is ignorant of theſe things, may be ſaid to haue no ſoule, as we reade of <hi>Ephraim, Who was ſaid to bec like a Doue deceiued without a heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſe</hi> 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>that is, without a ſoule:</hi> worldly wiſemen are euen like Moles and beaſts <hi>(In terra ſapienter ſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, ſupra nihil vident)</hi> They behaue themſelues orderly vpon Earth, but ſee nothing concerning the myſteries of Heauen, but it is the ſoule doth teach vs to vnderſtand wiſedome ſecretly, <hi>O giue mee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and I ſhall liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>(Iudicando praeſentia hoc iudicium ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil aliud eſt quam reddere cuique quod ſuum eſt)</hi> This iudgement is nothing elſe, but for vs to giue euery man his owne. Therefore let euery man ariſe, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Iudgement vpon the Throne of his ſoule, let his thoughts accuſe or excuſe, let his conſcience wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and let his memorie giue right Iudgement in all things concerning himſelfe, and God, and man; For himſelfe, let him forſake ſinne: For God, let him puniſh ſinne: For men let him doe good.</p>
            <p>Righteouſneſſe is nothing elſe but not to ſinne <hi>(Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus quod contra Iuſtitiam fecit per lachrimas punit)</hi> A iuſt man puniſheth that ſinne with teares, which hee hath committed by frailtie. <hi>If wee would iudge our ſelues, we ſhould not bee iudged,</hi> therefore, <hi>Whatſoeuer yee would that men ſhould doe vnto you, euen ſo doe yee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:23370:19"/>vnto them, for thus is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God hath ordained vs to bee Iudges in the Court of our conſciences, that we might arraigne our ſinnes and put them to death.</p>
            <p>This is the wiſedome of the ſoule, (neuer to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any, though neuer ſo good) if hee doe the things that are euill, and neuer to contradict any man (though neuer ſo euill,) if hee doe the thing that is good. This Iudgement can no waies bee ſo truely performed, as by the helpe of the memorie in our ſoules, one of the powers of the ſoule, that keepes the whole courſe of our life in the comlineſſe of good order.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>(expectando futura bona)</hi> expecting good things to come, which proceed from the grace of God through a good conſcience, and this is in the choyce of the will: Many things ſeeme hard to the vnwilling, but nothing is vneaſie to a good will, for if a ſmall reward in this life, makes vs eſteeme great labour little toyle; how much rather ſhould our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall reward of that bleſſedneſſe to come, make vs cheerfully to meet all confronting troubles, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably to expect all ſucceeding graces and offered bleſſings, which God hath aſſured to them that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diently ſerue him, who would not expect the reward promiſed, (yea though he be a ſinner) ſeeing God is mercifull: The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> thus reaſoneth with his fainted ſoule, Why art thou ſo heauie, O my ſoule! and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? O, put thy truſt in God, for I will yet giue him thanks which is the helpe of my countenance and my God. Three
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:23370:20"/>things doe moue the ſoule in willingneſſe, to waite for the bleſſings of Gods reward. Firſt, the Charitie of our adoption, who being ſlaues to Sinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, by Ieſus Chriſt, are now called, the ſonnes of God. Secondly, the truth of his promiſe, who is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forgetfull of his Couenant made to a thouſand generations. Thirdly, the poſſibilitie of his perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, to whom all power belongeth, and who is mercifull to reward euery man according to his works.</p>
            <p>The Husbandman patiently expecteth the fruits of the earth; and a good pawne is counted a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſecuritie: We haue Gods Word and Sacraments, and Chriſt himſelfe hath laid downe his life for vs <hi>(cum opus proficit praemij fiducia creſcit)</hi> when the worke is finiſhed, the expectation of the reward en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth: Thus, behold, wiſedome is infuſed into man by the powers of the ſoule, and this is the firſt qualitie to be obſerued in the ſoule <hi>(ſapientiam docet)</hi> it teacheth vs wiſedome.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>(munditiam ſeruat,)</hi> it preſerueth vs in innocencie and ſanctitie; the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> propounds a queſtion, and anſwereth himſelfe, Who ſhall aſſend into the Hill of the Lord, or who ſhall riſe vp in his holy place? euen hee, that hath cleane hands and a pure heart, and hath not lift vp his minde vnto vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic, nor ſworne to deceiue his Neighbour, hee ſhall receiue the bleſſing of the Lord and righteouſneſſe from the God of his ſaluation: And what part of man can performe this, but the ſoule? the ſoule and ſpirit only keeps the heart from euill thoughts, the mouth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:23370:20"/>from corrupt communication, the hands from hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full works, ſo that hereby wee are taught, the ſoule preſerueth vs innocent in heart, in word and in deede.</p>
            <p>No man putteth a precious oyntment which hee is deſirous to preſerue and keepe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cordis.</note> into a veſſell that hath beene vſed to filthie and corrupt ſauours, therefore waſh your hands, O ſinners, and cleanſe your hearts, you double minded; keepe your hearts cleane that would receiue the graces of God, for God will not ſend downe his grace to enter into that heart that is accuſtomed to ſinne. It is eaſier to make him rich that hath a great ſubſtance left of Parents, and is carefull to preſerue the ſame, then for the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, that hath already conſumed the inheritance of his fathers. So hee that yet hath preſerued the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of nature, may more eaſily be inriched with the graces of the Spirit, then hee that hath loſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie of his ſoule: The life and ſpirit, yea euen the vnderſtanding of the heart is of the ſoule, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in this one word, <hi>ſoule:</hi> this is the great Wheele, that ſets all the reſt agoing (vnto good or euill:) as it is, ſo are they euen all the parts and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the bodie; The innocencie of the ſoule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the forſaking of ſinne and following of grace, when we ceaſe to doe euill, and learne to doe well: if the heart be free from euill thoughts, all the bodie ſhall be free from ſinne; therefore when God willed <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to waſh her heart from wickedneſſe that ſhe might be ſaued (he concluded) <hi>how long ſhall euill thoughts remaine within you:</hi> there ſinne beginnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.14.</note>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:23370:21"/>there the rootes are faſtned, pluck vp the rootes then, and it ſhall bee impoſſible for ſinne to proſper. It was <hi>Dauids</hi> petition, <hi>Make me a cleane heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within mee.</hi> Thus you ſee the ſoule and ſpirit keepe the heart in innocencie, and ſo all the bodie ſhall be cleane from ſinne, alſo the ſoule and ſpirit of man, while hee liues, muſt keepe the mouth from corrupt communication:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Oris.</note> As in the tongue of a Swine, wee doe iudge of the ſoundneſſe of the bodie, ſo by the words of the mouth, the cleaneneſſe of the ſoule is conceiued; for when a good man openeth his mouth, behold, as it were in a temple, the glorious ſimilitude of a holy Soule: A good man out of the good treaſure of his ſoule bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth good things, therefore let no corrupt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication proceede out of your mouthes, but that which is good to the vſe of edifying, that yee may miniſter grace vnto the Hearers, and grieue not the holy Spirit of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iàm.</hi> 3.6.</note> By his euill words, wee know, that an euill mans tongue is ſet on fire of Hell; And by a good mans words,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.4.</note> we conceiue his tongue to be ſet on fire by the holy Ghoſt; therefore the holy Prophet exhorteth, <hi>O ſing yee praiſe with vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> no member without the bodie, no part or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie within the bodie is capeable of vnderſtanding, but by the ſoule, and only by the powers thereof is vnderſtanding infuſed into other parts, as you haue beene taught already: if therefore yee will grace your ſelues, and edifie your Brethren, and glorifie your God. O let your ſoules ſpeake firſt vnto your tongues, and be a watch vnto your mouthes, and ſet the ſeale
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:23370:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>of wiſedome vpon your lips, that ye may ſpeake with vnderſtanding, it is the phraſe of the wiſe <hi>Iew</hi> (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray beare with me,) The hearts of Fooles is in their mouth, but the mouth of the wiſe is in their heart. If therefore you deſire to bee counted wiſe and would not ſpeake like fooles, often let your ſoules take heede vnto your mouthes that you offend not in your tongue: according to your words will all men iudge of your liues, if your words be prophane, your conuerſation cannot be holy, if your words bee good, men will iudge your liues to bee honeſt; by good words the ſoule is delighted, by euill words the ſoule is grieued: But take heede if one of vs will ſcarce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide where wee haue rude and baſe entertainment, how much rather ſhall the holy Ghoſt (the ſoules gheſt) being daily diſquieted with blaſphemies, and diſgrac't with filthy talking, ſeeke to change her habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and leaue vs deſtitute of all grace. Againe, the ſoule muſt bee our guide and leade vs in our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that we may doe all things to the glorie of God. Grace is the life of the ſoule, by which only man is taught the knowledge of his ſinnes, the loue of God,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Operis.</hi>
               </note> and how to cleaue faſt vnto him, now it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for vs to iudge whether grace be in the ſoule of man or no, but by his outward actions: for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of the ſoule is knowne by the workes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, the worke ſhewes what the ſoule is, euery mans life is as his ſoule, therefore ſaith our Sauiour, let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in Heauen, and we ſay a wicked man hath an vnfaithfull
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:23370:22"/>ſoule; a good man is knowne by his workes, as a Tree by his fruits, do well then and men ſhall ſpeak well of thee. The ſoule moouing the members of the bodie to doe good, makes the whole man delightfull to be in the aſſembly of the faithfull, as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>I was glad when they ſaid vnto me; we will goe into the Houſe of the Lord, and all my delight ſhall bee in the Saints that dwell vpon Earth, and vpon ſuch as excell in Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo ſhe teacheth them innocencie in their priuate life, knowing that they are alwayes in the ſight of God, and therefore they abſtayne from all iniquitie; and ſhee teacheth them to deale iuſtly and charitably with all men Magiſtrates to deal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcionably in their Offices, Subiects to yeeld reuerent obedience to the Magiſtrates: briefly, ſo to liue one with another, that the fruits of our faith may be made manifeſt vnto all: and ſhee teacheth them of what calling or condition ſoeuer they be, ſo to exerciſe themſelues in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall vocations, that they may bee profitable and helpfull to themſelues, and priuate Families to the Church and members of God, and to the whole Common Wealth wherein they liue: Thus you ſee the qualitie of the ſoule to keepe vs innocent in our heart, our mouthes, and our workes, which God grant vnto vs for euermore.</p>
            <p>Thirdly <hi>(Conſtantiam nutrit)</hi> it nouriſheth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie: which is theſe three wayes <hi>(humiliter accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo)</hi> humbly taking vp our Croſſe: <hi>(patienter tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando)</hi> patiently bearing our afflictions: <hi>(fideliter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendo)</hi> faithfully louing our Fathers correction.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:23370:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>(humiliter accipiendo)</hi> while troubles doe aſſault vs, our ſoules are humbled within vs, there is giuen vs a pricke in the fleſh to buffet vs, leſt we ſhould be exalted aboue meaſure: the weake fleſh is readie to ſhunne all incumbrances, like the Sluggard that ſaith, <hi>There is a Lion in the way, and a Beare in the ſtreets:</hi> or the Spies that ſpake of the great Gyants of <hi>Anacke:</hi> but the valiant Spirit and ſoule makes vs willing to meete with any croſſe; and to embrace euery temptation cheerfully: As <hi>Iob</hi> when hee had loſt all his eſtate, and had no friends left him, rebuked his Wife for that ſhe would not willingly receiue euil at the hands of God aſwell as good; likewiſe holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſaid of <hi>Shimei,</hi> hee curſeth becauſe God hath bid him curſe <hi>Dauid:</hi> and as <hi>Paul</hi> flyeth not, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded not to goe vp to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but anſwered, <hi>I am readie not to be bound only, but alſo to dye at Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem for the Name of the Lord Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hath done halfe his worke that beginnes well, the willingneſſe of the ſoule, doth miniſter ſtrength to the Labourer, that he may not faint in the Worke of the Lord, nor be wearie of well-doing: It makes things that be moſt hard and difficult, to ſeeme eaſie to be done: therefore begin willingly, for by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall labour ſtrength is attayned, this willingneſſe is only in the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>(patienter tolerando)</hi> the ſtate of mans bodie is vtterly vncapeable of griefe, but the ſoule muſt beare the burthen of affliction: <hi>Lo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 13.15.</note> 
               <hi>though hee kill me, yet yet will I truſt in him:</hi> Patience is the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of the ſoule wherein it is preſerued from all iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:23370:23"/>of temptation: therefore when Chriſt our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour told his Diſciples of the ruines of the World, and terrours of the laſt times, hee wiſheth them to poſſeſſe their ſoules with patience. This makes the Prouerbe true <hi>(Vincit qui patitur)</hi> He that ſuffereth, ouercommeth; not with fighting, but with patient bearing: as <hi>Eleaſar,</hi> being readie to giue vp the ghoſt,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Mac.</hi> 11.30.</note> ſaid, <hi>The Lord knoweth manifestly, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I might haue beene deliuered from death, I am ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and ſuffer theſe ſore paines of my bodie, but in my minde I ſuffer them gladly for his Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtalke of a rotten Apple will not endure the leaſt winde without falling: ſo the patience of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull ſoule, will not endure the leaſt winde of temptation without falling into finall deſperation, as <hi>Achittophel</hi> and <hi>Iudas Iſcariot:</hi> What is the cauſe (beloued) that ſo many endure great labour, and take ſore paines to doe euill, and to wearie themſelues in the wayes of wickedneſſe, and we will not patiently endure the leaſt paines in the profitable paths of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and that ſome labour more for death then we for life, as Theeues and the wicked Iudges, is it not the corruption of an vnfaithfull ſoule? O then let vs not bee as naked men in the middeſt of our armed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: A raw Tyle caſt into the water is eaſily diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but being burnt in the Furnace doth wax hard and durable: ſo man liuing in the waters of ſinne is full of carnall pollution, but being burnt in the fire of holy loue, or in the furnace of tribulation, his ſoule is conſtant in holy deuotion: therefore as Beares are made fat by ſtripes, and the Aſſe is fedde with a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:23370:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>whip; and the <hi>Salamander</hi> delighteth in the fire: ſo let our ſoules take food and fatnes in temptation, and be delighted in the patience of true conſtancie fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>(fideliter diligendo)</hi> when wee conſider the ſweetneſſe of Gods mercie, ſparing when wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue puniſhment, &amp;c. How can wee but open our ſoules in loue and ſing to God, <hi>It is good for me that I haue bene troubled, &amp;c. Thy Rod and thy Staffe do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me, O how great is the multitude of thy Mercie, O Lord, The Lord is gracious vnto euery man, and his Mercie is ouer all his Workes:</hi> and it is an eſpeciall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Religion for loue of God, wiſely to auoyd the ſnares of the World, the Fleſh, and the Deuill: for the ſoule that is enlighted by God, doth driue away the wicked motions of temptation, as the Sunne draweth vp the miſts from the Earth, and this loue of the ſoule being firmely fixed vpon God, doth eaſily ouercome all feare, euen the feare of Pouertie, the feare of Death, and the feare of Iudgement; for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue caſteth out feare; and loue is ſtrong as death, <hi>Much water cannot quench loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>neither can the flouds drowne it: The loue of God is in vs, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the life of our ſoules;</hi> O then let our ſoules liue to prayſe him, God euen for his loue will not ſhrinke from vs; ſo let our ſoules in faithfull loue to him bee conſtant in all ſeruice appertayning to him, humbly to take vp our croſſe daily and follow him, patiently to endure his chaſtnings of loue, and faithfully to loue him for his gracious mercies towards vs, for his prouident preſeruation of our liues and eſtates, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:23370:24"/>for his mightie deliuerances out of all our temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And God almightie giue vs all grace to performe this truth for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third and laſt place wee are to conſider, the vtilitie and comfort of the ſoule, which is contained in theſe words (ſhall liue) carnally, we ſay, they that liue in mourning and miſerie, ſeeking for helpe of God, and ſeeing it yet farre from them, they are counted among the dead which be out of minde, and liue in the graue, and they that are <hi>(voti compotes)</hi> ſatisfied according to their hearts deſire, and frollick it in mirth and ioy, are ſaid to liue: And ſo ſpiritually wee ſay the ſoule that truely ſeeketh after God, onely delighting in the Lord may be truely ſaid to liue in God, theſe three wayes, firſt <hi>(per abſtractionem deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derij)</hi> by the reſtraint of his deſire: ſecondly, <hi>(per di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſitionem voluntatis)</hi> by the diſpoſition of his will; thirdly, <hi>(per praeſentiam adiutoris)</hi> by the preſence of his friend and helper.</p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>(per abſtractionem deſiderij)</hi> your ſoule ſhall liue (that is, it being now dead by ſinne, and dead by ſorrow, yet God ſhall ſpeake peace vnto your ſoules, and you ſhall liue being refreſhed with the bleſſing of peace) <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth of the deadly ebbe of his eſtate, how his enemies liue and are mightie; they come in, no misfortune like other folke, neither are they plagued like other men; but I am cleane forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as a dead man out of minde, and am become like a broken veſſell, and when he deſires to liue, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the manner hee would liue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 144.12.</note> (that our ſonnes may grow vp as the young plants; and that our daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:23370:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>may bee as the polliſhed corners of the Temple; that our Garners may bee full and plentious withall manner of ſtore; that our Sheepe may bring forth thouſands, and ten thouſands in our ſtreets; that our Oxen may be ſtrong to labour, that there bee no decay, no leading into captiuitie, and no complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in our ſtreets. O, this is a life indeed! happy are the people that be in ſuch a caſe, but the iuſt liue euen as well, in that they doe <hi>(abſtrahere deſiderium)</hi> reſtraine their deſires from carnall and temporall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights: The ſoule here is put for the life preſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all our life is in our ſoule; therefore the ſoules of the Saints doe euen now ſeeke heauen, as <hi>Paul</hi> who deſireth to be deſſolued and to bee with Chriſt: And <hi>Dauid</hi> hath rather to bee a dore-keeper in the Houſe of God, then to dwell in the Tents of vngodlineſſe; <hi>Zacheus</hi> ſo farre reſtrained his greedie appetite, that he gaue halfe of that he had to the poore, and reſtored his wrongs done to any foure-fold; and the Prodigall conſidering his Fathers bountie, will bee no more a ſonne, but a hired ſeruant; and ſurely, beloued, if we did but once taſte in our ſoules the gracious mercy of God towards vs, we ſhould haue leſſe reſpect to the world, and more care to receiue heauen: giue to your ſoules the fulneſſe of all pleaſure, which <hi>Salomon</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed, and with him you will crie out, All is but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and vexation of ſpirit: or let ſoules chooſe any peculiar delight that this world can afford to comfort her, yet will ſhee not be ſatisfied, ſeeing God alone is the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of all her happineſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I exhort and beſeech you all (beloued in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:23370:25"/>Lord) put a bridle vpon your affections to reſtraine thoſe boundleſſe and vngodly luſts, whereto our fleſh is too too prone, and ſeeke after God in your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits with truth, that your ſoules may liue in peace and ioy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſoule is ſaid to liue <hi>(per diſpoſitionem voluntatis)</hi> by the godly diſpoſition of her will. A faithfull ſoule is the Houſe of God, becauſe God is ſed to dwell in her, in this life preſent, by the ſweet taſte of his gracious loue adminiſtred vnto her; and in the life to come, by the bleſſed fruition of his glory: (now) it is moſt meete that euery Maſter or Lord ſhould haue command of his houſe, and ſo ſhould God of our ſoules; therefore it is our dutie, euen as Chriſt hath taught vs, to ſubmit our will to his will; not my will, but thine be fulfilled, <hi>thy will be done in earth as in heauen:</hi> O Father, from this time forth for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſoule may be ſaid to liue <hi>(per diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem voluntatis)</hi> by the diſpoſition of her will, which ought to be conformed according to the will of God, and that is, that no man ſhould go beyond the ſtatutes of Gods holy Law and Commandements; and that euery man, as farre as poſſibly he may in all things, ſhould conforme his will vnto the diuine will and pleaſure of God; according to the ſaying of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, If any man will come after me, let him denie himſelfe, and take vp his croſſe daily and follow mee; for the wicked doe not ceaſe to ſinne, though they haue no power to performe ſinne, and though they haue no meanes or oportunitie to act ſinne yet haue
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:23370:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>not left their will and minde to ſinne; if they might be ſuffered; as wee may ſay of Infancie, Sickneſſe, Old-age and Captiuitie, the will is the roote (planted in the ſoule) the words and workes of a man are but the fruites, and its vnprofitable that other branches ſhould ſpring forth, but ſuch as the roote in the earth doth yeeld; a will well diſpoſed of all other good gifts of God is certainly to bee accounted the chiefe gift vnto mans ſaluation, for from a good will all good workes are produced, and where a ſlaue doth liue in ſeruile feare, and hath a will to reuenge, hee would aſſuredly performe as much if he were as ſure to ſcape puniſhment; the zeale of a good will ſhould increaſe by loue, as fire doth by the addition of wood.</p>
            <p>As in the two ſiſters <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> there were two wils, that is to ſay, Actiue and Contemplatiue, and both were harmeleſſe and laudable, ſo it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the ſoule to enter into the heauenly Countrey that is not exerciſed in one of theſe, that is, a willing deſire alwayes to practiſe the workes of mercie, both by charitable gifts and godly counſaile to the Brethren, or alwayes to bee deuoted vnto the holineſſe of godly meditation, making the Law of God the Glaſſe of his life, the wordes of God the path of his way, and the examples of the Saints the patterne of all his workes: theſe are the two wings of the ſoule whereby it may be lifted vp to Heauen.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the continuall meditation of Gods mercie: Secondly, the faithfull aſſurance and confidence we haue in our Mediator Ieſus Chriſt. Why doeſt thou ſtraggle and runne aſtray, O wretched man, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:23370:26"/>many things? ſeeking reſt and comfort to thy ſoule and bodie, loue one thing which ſhall ſuffice thee, for all things whatſoeuer thou deſireſt (tell mee, O my ſoule) where is that thou loueſt, where is that thou deſireſt, ſure it can no where elſe be found, but where it can neuer bee loſt, euen where Chriſt raigneth for euermore in glorie? the life of the bodie is the ſoule, and the life of the ſoule is GOD, <hi>O then delight thy ſelfe in the LORD, and he ſhall giue thee the deſires of thy ſoule,</hi> O liue in God and bee drawne to euerlaſting life and glorie by his loue, <hi>For hee that liueth vnto God, is dead vnto ſinne; and hee that liueth vnto ſinne, is dead before God;</hi> therefore let the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of your ſoule winne you to the loue of God: let the qualitie of your ſoules worke in you the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God, and let the vtilitie and comfort of your ſoules driue you continually to ſeeke after God: <hi>O ſeeke after God and your ſoules ſhall liue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, the ſoule may bee ſaid to liue <hi>(per praeſentiam adiutoris)</hi> by the ſudden preſence of his friend and helper, many man fainting and readie to periſh in the raging fury of their enemies,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.3</note> as <hi>Dauid,</hi> when <hi>Ionathan</hi> comforted him, was againe refreſhed and as a man reuiued with life, confirmed his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vntill he had poſſeſt the promiſe of his Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with peace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1.</note>
               <hi>Abrahams</hi> heart was dead, yet when God told him, <hi>I am thy buckler and exceeding great reward, the feare which he had of fiue Kings, was with him accounted nothing:</hi> ſo when the iuſt who are accounted as the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:23370:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Apple of Gods eye, and the Signet of his right arme are incompaſſed with all manner of troubles, their hearts are ſtabliſhed and ſhrinke not, <hi>For if God bee with vs,</hi> ſay they, <hi>who ſhall be againſt vs:</hi> Thus when you behold the dignitie, qualitie, vtilitie, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Loue God aboue all; be patient in all things, and bee aſſuredly refreſhed in the hope of Gods ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-fayling helpe. Which God Almightie grant vs euer to performe through Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23370:27"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23370:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
